A Guide to the Strauss Family Papers, 1839-1938
Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
The Papers of the Strauss Family, 1839-1938
Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
MG 9
3.5 linear feet, 7 document cases, one card box
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open to researchers without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Marjory S. Strauss, September 1976.
Biographical/Historical Information
Arthur Strauss, the main focus of the collection, was a physician, poet, art collector, and painter. He was born in 1864 in Halle, Westphalia, Germany. His father, Abraham Strauss, was a physician. Arthur studied medicine and received his medical diploma in 1888. He specialized in Dermatology and published a textbook on skin diseases in 1895. He settled in Barmen, Germany where he had a successful medical practice. In 1900 Arthur married Lucy Hertz. Arthur and Lucy traveled extensively throughout Europe and also to the east coast of the United States. Many of the letters in the collection were written during these travels.
Arthur and Lucy had one son, Arnold, in 1902 who also became a physician. Arnold worked as a pathologist at a hospital in Berlin. In 1933 Adolf Hitler came into power in Germany and began to implement his policies against Jews. Because the Strauss' were of Jewish ancestry they were subject to these discriminative policies and found it hard to continue to work. In 1933 Arnold and his parents immigrated to the Netherlands. In 1935 Arnold secured a position at St. Vincent's Hospital in Norfolk, Virginia and immigrated to the United States. Arthur who was a very patriotic man and loved Germany greatly, was reluctant to leave Europe. It wasn't until 1938 that he finally gave up hope of returning to Germany and agreed to immigrate to the United States. Thus when Arnold began trying to obtain immigrant visas for them to join him in the United States it was probably too late due to the large numbers of people also trying to leave Europe at the time. He also unsuccessfully tried to obtain an immigration visa for his fiancee, Irmgard Keun, a German author. When the German army invaded the Netherlands in May 1940 the Strauss' became trapped there. Arthur and Lucy Strauss endured four months of the Nazi occupation of the Netherlands. Then after apparently losing hope of being able to join Arnold in the United States they took their own lives in September 1940. Arnold's long-distance relationship with Keun eventually came to an end as well. In 1941 Arnold married an American, Marjory Ware Spindle. Arnold died in 1965.
Scope and Content Information
The Strauss collection covers the years 1839 to 1938. The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence between Arthur and Lucy Strauss between the years of 1900 and 1933. Also included is correspondence with their son, Arnold Strauss. Most of the collection is in German. In addition to correspondence the collection includes publications, newspaper clippings, typed manuscripts of works by Irmgard Keun, record books, legal documents, and school records for Abraham, Lucy, and Arnold Strauss.
Arrangement
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically within each series. The postcards, photographs, and calling cards are not arranged chronologically as most of them are not dated.
Organization
The collection is divided into four series: Series I-Personal Correspondence, Series II-Publications, Series III-Certificates and Legal Documents, Series IV-Miscellaneous.
Series I: Personal Correspondence ranges from 1863 to 1938. The series includes correspondence between family and friends. All but a few letters are in German.
Series II: Publications ranges from 1844 to 1935. The series includes published articles by Arthur Strauss and Arnold Strauss. Also included are two reprints from "Der Beobachter," a copy of "Bericht 1915- 1917 Nationaler Frauendienst," and "Wieder Liebesbriefe" containing a poem by Irmgard Keun. There are two articles about Keun and other German women writers. Other newspaper clippings are from the Barmen newspaper and the "Women's Page" of the Frankfurt newspaper. All publications are in German.
Series III: Certificates and Legal Documents range from 1839 to 1918. This series includes certificates to practice medicine, documents regarding service in the army as a physician, and certificates of donations to the national treasury. School documents are also included such as grade reports, certificates of graduation and other academic documents. Most of these documents are in German, and a few of the academic certificates are in Latin.
Series IV: Miscellaneous includes undated manuscripts of works by Irmgard Keun, poetry by unknown authors, financial record books, post cards and picture postcards from the early 20th century, photographs, and calling cards.
Related Materials
Keun, Irmgard. "Ich lebe in einem wilden Wirbel: Briefe an Arnold Strauss 1933 bis 1947." Selected and edited by Gabriele Dries and Marjory S. Strauss. Dusseldorf: Claassen, 1988. In German.
This book is not part of the Strauss collection but is held in the Perry Library's general collection. The book tells the story of Arnold Strauss and Irmgard Keun's relationship through their letters.
Contents List
- Personal Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1863 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, March 1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, April 1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, May-June 1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, July-December 1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1865 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1866 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1888-1895 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, January-May 1900 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, June-July 1900 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, August-September 1900 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, October-December 1900 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, January-April 1901 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, May-July 1901 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, August-September 1901 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, October 1901 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, November-December 1901 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, January 1902 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, January 1902 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, February 1902 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, March 1902 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, April-June 1902 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, July-August 1902 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, September-October 1902 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, November-December 1902 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, January-April 1903 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, May-August 1903 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, September-December 1903 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, January-June 1904 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, July-November 1904 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1905-1907 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1908 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, January-July 1909 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, September 1909 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, October 1909 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1910-1914 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1915-1938 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, not dated I (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, not dated II (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, not dated III (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, not dated IV (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, not dated V (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, not dated VI (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, not dated VII (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, not dated VIII (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, not dated IX (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 7)
- Publications
  - Publications by Arthur Strauss, 1872, 1885 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Publications by Arnold Strauss, 1927 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Other Publications, 1844, 1917, not dated (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Publications pertaining to Irmgard Keun, 1932-1933 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1905, 1911, 1935 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 5)
- Certificates, Legal Documents
  - School Certificates, Grade Reports, 1840-1847 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 6)
  - School Certificates, Grade Reports, 1885-1888 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Medical and Army Medical Service, 1839-1918 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Other Certificates, 1917 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 9)
- Miscellaneous
  - Irmgard Keun Manuscripts, not dated (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Poetry, not dated (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Record Books, 1909-1933 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Papers (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Picture Postcards (Box Box 8)
  - Photographs (Box Box 8)
  - Postcards (Box Box 8)
  - Calling Cards (Box Box 8)